<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Truth ascended, or, The annointed and sealed of God defended in an answer written by Richard Farnsworth as a testimony against a conterfeit commission and all injustice and false judgement done and pronounced under pretence of the same.</title>
            <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1663</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 77 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40953</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F511</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R37783</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17018461</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17018461</idno>
            <idno type="VID">105803</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40953)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 105803)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1615:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Truth ascended, or, The annointed and sealed of God defended in an answer written by Richard Farnsworth as a testimony against a conterfeit commission and all injustice and false judgement done and pronounced under pretence of the same.</title>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London printed :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Muggleton, Lodowick, 1609-1698.</term>
               <term>Reeve, John, 1608-1658.</term>
               <term>Society of Friends --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:105803:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Truth Aſcended, OR, <hi>The Annointed and Sealed of God defended.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>IN AN ANSWER Written by Richard Farnſworth, AS A TESTIMONY AGAINST A Conterfeit Commisſion</p>
            <p>And all Injuſtice and falſe Judgement done and pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced under pretence of the ſame.</p>
            <p>LONDON, Printed in the Year, 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:105803:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:105803:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>Truth aſcended, or the Annointed and ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God defended, &amp;c.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Lodowick Muggleton,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THough thou pretend to be the choſen Witneſs of the Spirit, and the laſt that ever ſhall ſpeak by Commiſſion from God; and to be the chief Judge in the World ordained of God to give ſentence upon men and women ſpiritual and eternal, and what ſhall become of them after death; and ſaiſt, <hi>That in obedience to thy Commiſſion thou haſt already curſed and damned many hundreds of people both body and ſoul from the preſence of God; elect men and Angels to Eternity;</hi> and pretend'ſt <hi>to go by as certain Rule (in ſo doing) as the Judges of the Land do when they give Judgement according to Law;</hi> and ſaiſt, <hi>That no infinite Spirit of Chriſt, nor any God can; or ſhall be able to deliver from thy ſentence and curſe, &amp;c.</hi> as appears in a Sheet of paper; dated <hi>Aug.</hi> 10. 1662. written by thee in anſwer to <hi>Edward Bourns</hi> to <hi>Dorothy Carter;</hi> and alſo four ſheets dated <hi>Novemb.</hi> 3. 1662. written by thee, and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to <hi>Thomas Highfield</hi> in <hi>Nottingham,</hi> for <hi>Samuel Hooton</hi> and <hi>W. S.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am bold (on the behalf of the Lord) once again to bear my Teſtimony againſt thee, and againſt thy pretended Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and the Doctrine thereof, and ſhall make it appear, that it ought not to be entertained by any man or woman upon earth, becauſe it is contrary to truth, and that thy judgment ought by all to be reverſed, undone, and made void, becauſe it is contrary to truth; and that thy judgement ought by all to be reverſed, undone and made void, becauſe it is erroneous and falſe; for thou art no choſen Witneſſe of the Spirit of Truth, neither haſt thou received any Commiſſion from Chriſt, to
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:105803:3" rendition="simple:additions"/>whom all the Prophets gave witneſſe, as hereafter ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That there were choſen Witneſſes of Chriſt to whom all the Prophets gave witneſſe, is certainly true, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.38, 39, 40, 41. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31 32. <hi>Acts</hi> 1.8.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That they had a Commiſſion from Chriſt, to whom all the Prophets gave witneſs; or, that he Commanded them to preach to the people, is as true, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.42. But that thou either art, or doſt ſo, I do deny.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They who were choſen Witneſſes of Chriſt (whom God the Father annointed, ſealed and ſent) and had a Commiſſion from the Spirit and Power of Chriſt, to whom all the Prophets gave witneſs, in teſtifying on the behalf of Chriſt; their Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony ſtands as an evidence againſt thy pretended Commiſſion, and the Doctrine thereof (becauſe they ſay (on the behalf of Chriſt) that he commanded them to preach to the people, and to teſtifie to them, that it is he which was ordained of God to be the Judge of quick and dead, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.42. <hi>To him give all the Prophets witneſs, that through his Name whoſoever believeth in him, ſhall receive remiſſion of ſins,</hi> Acts 10.43. But thou doſt not ſo by thy pretended Commiſſion, and the Doctrine thereof, who in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of preaching to the people, and teſtifying to them, that Chriſt is chief Judge ordained of God to judge the quick and the dead, thou wouldſt diſ-throne him to ſet up thy ſelf in his ſtead; whereby it appears, That thou art not a choſen Witneſs of the Spirit of Truth, and that thy pretended Commiſſion is a counterfeit thing, by which thou preſumes to give judgement contrary to Truth, which makes it evident, That thy doctrine and judgement is falſe, and being ſo, it ought not to be enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained or received by any, but to be denied, and againſt teſtifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by all that love the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p n="4">4. By their Commiſſion they were to preach to the people, and by the ſame Commiſſion, and the Doctrine thereof, they were to teſtifie to them, that Chriſt was ordained of God to be the Judge both of quick and dead; but thou art not Chriſt to whom all the Prophets gave witneſs; therefore it is evident, that thou art not chief Judge ordained of God to judge the quick and the dead; though thou preſume to ſay, that the dead af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:105803:3"/>death ſhall never ſee any other God or Judge, but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of that ſentence which you the pretended Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes of the Spirit did paſs upon them in this life, which is a falſe Doctrine, and contrary to the Doctrine of Truth left up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on record in Scripture, where it is ſaid, <hi>That the Father hath gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven authority to the Son to execute judgement, and all that are in the grave ſhall hear his voice, and ſhall come forth, they that have done good unto the reſurrection of Life, and they that have done evil unto the reſurrection of damnation;</hi> as it is written <hi>John</hi> 5.26, 27, 28, 29. and Chriſt ſhall give judgement upon them, Matth. 25.31, 32, 33, 34.41.46.</p>
            <p>And as thou wouldſt exclude Chriſt from that great office and work, and aſſume it to thy ſelf, ſo thou wouldſt exclude his Officers, and deny him of them, to ſet up thy ſelf alone in their places and ſtead, becauſe thou falſly ſaith, No man knows the Scriptures but thy ſelf; and that no man can truly interpret the Scriptures but thy ſelf; and that none ought to officiate the Office of a Miniſter, Meſſenger or Ambaſſador of Chriſt, but ſuch as are appointed by <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf; which aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions or doctrines of thine are falſe, and not true; for this I ſay, That the only knowledge and right of interpreting Scriptures, belongs not to thy ſelf, but to the Lord Jeſus and his bleſſed Spirit, who is the true Judge, and hath power to open mens underſtandings, and can give them the true knowledge, and right underſtanding of Scriptures, <hi>Luke</hi> 24 32. &amp; 24.45.</p>
            <p>And the Goſpel is preached with the Holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven, as it is written 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.11, 12. and the holy Ghoſt hath a true power and right Authority (without <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf) to make overſeers over the Flock of God, to feed the Church of God which he hath purchaſed with his own blood, <hi>Acts</hi> 20.28. and to appoint Miniſters, Meſſengers or Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors of Chriſt, and to call to the work of the Miniſtry, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.2 4. And they who by the Holy Ghoſt are called to the Work of the Miniſtry, may with the Holy Ghoſt ſent down from Heaven, preach the Goſpel without the appointment of <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf. Take notice of that; for <hi>as every man hath received the gift, even ſo miniſter the ſame one to another, as good ſtewards of the manifold grace of God; if any man ſpeak, let him ſpeak
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:105803:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>as the Oracles of God; if any man miniſter, let him do it as of the abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity which God giveth, that God in all things may be glorified through Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt,</hi> as it is written and left upon Record in Scripture, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4 10, 11.</p>
            <p n="5">5. The choſen Witneſſes of Chriſt who had a Commiſſion from his bleſſed Spirit, they were anointed, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21. and ſealed of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.22. but ſo art not thou; therefore thou art no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing like unto them; and they who are annointed and ſeal d of God as ſuch were, they may be Miniſters, Meſſengers and Ambaſſadors of Chriſt now, without the appointment of <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf; neither art thou at all owned by the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine of their commiſſion, (to do as thou doſt, and pretendeſt to do under pretence of thy pretended commiſſion) it takes no notice of thee, and ſuch as thou art, to appoint to ſo great and glorious a Work, though thou preſume in thy imaginati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to be greater then either Prophets of God, or Apoſtles of Chriſt, yet thou never approved thy ſelf to be a Meſſenger, Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter or Ambaſſador of Chriſt, as they do and did, who are and were annointed, ſealed and ſent of God as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p n="6">6. For the Ambaſſadors who had a commiſſion to preach, and were annointed and ſealed of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.21, 22. and had the Miniſtration of reconciliation given unto them, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.18, 19, 20. a glorious Miniſtration, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.8, 9, 10, 11. which is the Miniſtration of the Spirit, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.5 6. their ſufficiency was (not of any, like <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf, but) of God, who made them (and hath the ſame power now, without <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf, to make) able Miniſters of the New-Teſtament, they approved themſelves as the Miniſters of God (not by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viling, curſing and damning, but on the contrary) in much pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience, in afflictions, in neceſſities, in diſtreſſes, in ſtripes, in im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priſonments, in labours, in watchings, in faſtings, by pureneſs, by knowledge, by long-ſuffering, by kindneſs, by the holy Ghoſt, by love unfeigned, by the Word of truth, and by the power of God; See 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.4, 5, 6, 7, 8 9, 10. And the Meſſengers of Chriſt, whoſe ſufficiency is (not of <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf, but) of God, who (by virtue of his bleſſed power and ſpirit) are made able Miniſters of the New-Teſtament, and are ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually annointed and ſealed of God, they ſtand approved to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:105803:4"/>God, as the Miniſters of God, according to Goſpel-order, and the diſpenſation of the Goſpel, which is the Miniſtration of the Spirit; but thou haſt not ſo approved thy ſelf, who fled from <hi>Cheſterfield</hi> to <hi>Bakwell</hi> for fear of a few ſtripes, or a whipping, when the ſame was but threatned againſt thee for thy falſe Judgement and Doctrine in reviling, curſing and damning; whereby it is evident, that thou art nothing like an Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of Chriſt, and very unfit to appoint to that work, and that thy pretended Commiſſion, and the greatneſſe of thy pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed power is nothing worth: Take notice of that.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The Ambaſſadors of Chriſt who were annointed and ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God, and had the Miniſtration of Reconciliation given unto them, that glorious Miniſtration of the Spirit, wherein they approved themſelves as the Miniſters of God (which thou haſt not done) they were ſo far from reviling, curſing and damning, and rejoicing therein, as thou doſt, that they forgave in the perſon of Chriſt, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2.10. and by manifeſtation of the Truth, commended themſelves to every man's conſcience in the ſight of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1, 2. but thou doſt not ſo, who art ſo full of reviling, curſing and damning; whereby it's apparent, that thy pretended Commiſſion, Power and Doctrine thereof, is nothing like unto theirs; though thou falſly ſaiſt, it's as true and of a more higher nature then theirs was in their time; thou haſt lyed therein, and haſt born a falſe Teſtimony, which makes it evident, that thou art no choſen Witneſſe of the Spirit of Truth.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Ambaſſadors of Chriſt who were annointed and ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led of God, and had the glorious Miniſtration of the Spirit gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven unto them, by virtue of their commiſſion of the Spirit, and the doctrine thereof, they commanded for to prove all things, and hold faſt that which is good; and to try the ſpirits whether they be of God; becauſe many falſe Prophets are gone out into the World, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 5.21. 1 <hi>John</hi> 4.1. to the end that they might not entertain the Doctrine of any falſe Prophet, nor bid ſuch God ſpead as abide not in the doctrine of Chriſt, leſt they become partakers of their evil-deed, 2 <hi>John</hi> 9.10, 11. but by the Doctrine of thy pretended commiſſion thou denies that, <hi>viz</hi> proving of doctrines, and trying of ſpirits, ſaying,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:105803:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <hi>That neither the Light of Chriſt within, nor no man upon earth can, or ought to judge of the Doctrine, becauſe</hi> (thou ſaiſt) <hi>that neither the Light within, nor no man upon Earth can, or ought to judge of the Doctrine of a Prophet, who hath a Commiſſion from God;</hi> and ſaiſt, <hi>That there neither is, nor ever ſhall be any ſuch Prophet but thy ſelf whilſt the World doth endure;</hi> which is a falſe aſſertion or doctrine of thine, but hereby it is manifeſt, that thou art a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt trying of ſpirits, and proving of Doctrines, and ſo art againſt the reception thereof, becauſe Judgement in point of Doctrine, is in order to the reception of Doctrine. And for want of judgement in that reſpect, they may be deceived, who take doctrines upon truſt without judging &amp; trying thereof, &amp; how ſhould ſpirits be tryed, and doctrines be proved? or how ſhould the Doctrine of Truth be performed, which commands to try and prove them, if none can or ought (as thou falſly ſaiſt) to judge of the ſame: Whereby it appears that thou art not the choſen Witneſſe of the Spirit of Truth, and that thy doctrine is contrary to the doctrine of truth, and ought not to be recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved by any man upon earth; and it is evident thereby, that thy pretended commiſſion is a counterfeit thing, invented to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guile and deceive withal, and not at all owned by the commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and doctrine of the Ambaſſadors of the Lord Jeſus, who were and are annointed and ſealed of God.</p>
            <p n="9">9. The Ambaſſadors of Chriſt, and choſen Witneſſes of the Spirit, who were annointed and ſealed of God, they were workers together with God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.1. and did pray in Chriſt's ſtead, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.20. but thou doſt not ſo, who inſtead thereof, goes about reviling, curſing and damning the beloved people of God, who preach from the Scriptures and Light within, and by vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of the power which they have received of God, Devils are caſt out, and (as thou ſaiſt) much good is done by them, who ought not to be reviled and curſed by thee as they are; whereby it appears that thou art no choſen Witneſſe of the Spirit of Truth, nor an Ambaſſador of Chriſt, neither art thou annoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and ſealed, or ſent of God to go about reviling, curſing and damning the beloved people of God, as thou doſt; for they who were the choſen Witneſſes of the Spirit, and Ambaſſadors of Chriſt, did not ſo; but thou haſt exceeded <hi>Balaam</hi> in that,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:105803:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>who refuſed to curſe thoſe whom God had bleſſed. And the Ambaſſadors of Chriſt, annointed, ſealed and ſent of God, they approved themſelves as the choſen Witneſſes of the Spirit, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed and ſealed of God, who being defamed, did entreat; and being perſecuted, did ſuffer it, and not flee, as thou didſt, for fear of a whipping threatned againſt thee for thy miſ-be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haviour in reviling, curſing and damning; the choſen Witneſſes of the Spirit annointed and ſealed of God, did not ſo, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing reviled, did bleſſe, and by the Doctrine of their Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, ſaid, <hi>Bleſs, and curſe not,</hi> 1 Cor. 4.12. Rom. 12.14. whereby it is evident, that thou art not a choſen Witneſſe of the Spirit of Truth, neither art thou annointed and ſealed, or ſent by the God of Truth; thy pretended Commiſſion, and the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine thereof, and Judgement performed thereby, is errone<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and falſe, which is Antichriſtian; and it is no railing to tell thee the ſame, and reprove thee and thy deceit.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The true Witneſſes of the Spirit, and Ambaſſadors of Chriſt, by the Father of mercies and God of all comfort, they were comforted themſelves in all their tribulations, that they might be able to comfort them that were in any trouble, by the comfort wherewith they themſelves were comforted of God, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 1 3, 4. but ſo art not thou by thy reviling, curſing and damning them who are bleſſed, beloved and juſtified of God, wherein thou haſt exceeded <hi>Balaam</hi> as aforeſaid, whereby it appears, that thou art nothing like an Ambaſſador of Chriſt, or the choſen Witneſſes of the Spirit who were annointed and ſealed of God; neither is there the like Truth, Power, Virtue and Conſolation in the doctrine of thy pretended commiſſion that were in theirs. Thou haſt grievouſly lyed in ſaying, <hi>That the Doctrine of thy Commiſſion is as true, and of a more higher nature then the Prophets and Apoſtles was in their time;</hi> but haſt made no ſuch proof of thy ſayings or Doctrine as they did of theirs; But thou art reprehended, and the truth and power of the Commiſſion and Doctrine of the annointed and ſealed of God is defended; and the truth of the Goſpel is over and above all thy errors, lyes and falſe judgement aſcended.</p>
            <p>By all which hath been ſaid, it remains true, 1. That thou art no choſen Witneſſe of the Spirit of Truth. 2. That thou
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:105803:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>art not the chief Judge in the World ordained of God to judge the quick and the dead. 3. That God may (without <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf) make able Miniſters of the New-Teſtament. 4. That they who are made able Miniſters of the New-Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, whoſe ſufficiency is not of ſelf, but of God, they may officiate the Offices of Miniſters, Meſſengers, or Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dors of Chriſt, without the appointment of <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf, who hath nothing to do to appoint to ſo great and glorious Work. 5. That thou art not annointed, ſealed and ſent of God to revile, curſe and damn the beloved people of God. 6. That thou art no Ambaſſador of Chriſt to whom all the Prophets gave witneſs. 7. That thou haſt received no Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from the God of Truth to paſs the ſentence of eternal death and damnation upon the ſouls and bodies of men. 8. That the only knowledge and right of interpreting Scripture, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs not to thee. 9. That thy Judgement and Doctrine is er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>roneous and falſe. And <hi>10thly,</hi> That thy Judgement and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine ought not to be entertained by any, but to be reverſed and denyed by all that love the Lord Jeſus.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſaiſt, <hi>Thou art the chief Judge in the World, and in paſſing the Sentence of eternal death and damnation upon the ſouls and bodies of men,</hi> ſaiſt, <hi>Thou goes by as certain a Rule as the Judges of the Land do when they give Judgement according to Law;</hi> I ſay, Thou haſt lyed therein, and haſt born a falſe teſtimony in that reſpect as well as the reſt, as hereafter is evident.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe thou art both Judge, Accuſer and Witneſs thy ſelf, and doſt condemn and give Judgement at thy will and pleaſure, contrary to Truth, having no certain known Laws ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God or the Land, as a rule of direction to guide and lead thee in the wayes of right Juſtice, to give Judgement up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bodies of men and women, nor cannot manifeſt a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion to put any known Laws in execution upon them; thou goes not by ſo certain a Rule (in ſo doing) as the Judges of the Land do when they give judgement according to Law; for they neither are, nor pretend to be both Judges, Accuſers and Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes; neither do they go without certain outward known Laws as a rule of direction to guide and lead them to give Judgement accordingly; and they can produce a commiſſion
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:105803:6" rendition="simple:additions"/>whereby they are impowered to put the ſame in execution; but ſo canſt not thou: Whereby it is evident, that thou haſt not cognizance or lawful authority to paſs the ſentence of death upon the bodies of men and women: Therefore thou art no true and competent Judge in that matter; take notice of that.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Thou goes not by ſo certain a Rule when thou preſumes to paſs the ſentence of death and damnation upon the ſouls and bodies of men, as the Judges of the Land do when they give judgement according to Law; for <hi>Cook</hi> upon the confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the Charters of the Liberties of <hi>England,</hi> ſaith, <hi>This Clauſe is worthy to be written in Letters of Gold,</hi> viz.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That our Juſtices, Sheriffs, Mayors and other Miniſters which under us have the Laws of the Land to guide them, ſhall allow the ſaid Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in all their points which ſhall come before them in Judgement; and here it is to be obſerved, That the Laws are the Judges Guides and Lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, according to that old Rule,</hi> Lex eſt exercitus Judicum; <hi>viz. The Law is the Judges Army.</hi> Tutiſſimus Doctor. Viz. <hi>The ſafeſt Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher. Or,</hi> Lex eſt optimus Judicis Synagogus; viz. <hi>Their beſt Sy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue. And,</hi> Lex eſt tutiſſimus Caſſis; viz. <hi>Their ſafeſt fortreſs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>There is an old Legal word</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>called</hi> Guidagium, <hi>viz. Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dage, which ſignifieth an Office of guiding Travellers through dangerous and unknown ways: Here it appeareth, that the Laws of the Realm hath this office to guide the Judges in all cauſes that come before them in the wayes of right Juſtice, who never yet miſ-guided any man that certain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly knew them, and truly followed them.</hi> Cook part 2. Inſt. fol. 566.</p>
            <p>Whereby it is apparent, That the Judges of the Land have certain outward known Laws as a Rule of direction to guide and lead them to Judgement, when they give it according to Law; but thon <hi>(Lodowick)</hi> haſt no certain outward known Laws either of God or the Land, as a Rule of direction to guide thee in the ways of right Juſtice, and to lead thee to give judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon the bodies of men accordingly; whereby it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, thou haſt nothing to do to paſs the ſentence of death and damnation upon them: And the ſouls in the Fathers hands thou haſt nothing to do withal, neither doſt thou go by ſo cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Rule to give judgement upon the bodies of men, as the Judges of the Land do when they give judgement according
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:105803:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>to Law. Mind how thou art confuted and taken with a lye in thy mouth. Behold how the pretended moſt knowing and wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſt of men is taken in his own craftineſs! Let no man deceive himſelf, for the wiſdom of this World is fooliſhneſs with God; for it is written, <hi>He taketh the wiſe in their own craftineſs;</hi> and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, <hi>The Lord knoweth the thoughts of tht wiſe, that they are vain;</hi> 1 Cor. 3 18, 19, 20. Thou art ſnared with the words of thy mouth; thou art taken with the words of thy mouth, Prov. 6 2. <hi>The wicked is ſnared by the tranſgreſſion of his lips,</hi> Prov. 12.13. and ſo art thou; take notice of that.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Thou goes not by ſo certain a Rule to give judgment and ſentence of death and damnation upon the ſouls and bodies of men, as the Judges of the Land do when they give judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to Law; for by the Law (which is a Rule of direction to them) it is enacted, <hi>That no man from thenceforth ſhall be attached by any accuſation, nor fore-adjudged of Life nor Limb, &amp;c. againſt the form of the great Charter, and the Law of the Land,</hi> 5 Edw. 3.25 Edw. 3. Cook, part 2. Inſt. fol. 48.</p>
            <p>But thou <hi>Lodowick</hi> fore-judges the ſouls and bodies of men from the preſence of God, elect men and Angels to Eternity, contrary to the Law of God, and the Law of the Land; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by it appears that thou goes by no Legal Rule, neither accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Law of the Land, nor the Law of God; for thou ſaiſt, That the ſentence and curſe which thou pronounceſt upon the ſouls and bodies of men, is not from the Scriptures, or Light within, then not according to the Law of God, and as before is proved, it is quite contrary to the Law of the Land.</p>
            <p>What then is thy Rule of direction to give judgement upon the ſouls and bodies of men, ſeeing thou pretends to be the chief Judge in the World, and gives not thy judgement and ſentence according to the Law of God? Produce us thy Law and commiſſion if thou canſt, now thou art put to it, for thou neither goes by the Law of God either without or within, nor by ſo certain a Rule as the Judges of the Land do when they give judgement according to Law; therefore thou goes not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the Law of the Land, and it is evident, That thou goes not according to the Law of God as aforeſaid.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:105803:7" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Seeing then, that the Judges of the Land have certain out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward known Laws, as a rule of direction to guide and lead them to give judgement upon the bodies of men, and an outward commiſſion to impower them to put the ſame in execution; and thou pretends to be a Judge to paſs the ſentence of death up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on men and women, and pretends (in ſo doing) to go by as cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain a Rule as the Judges of the Land do when they give judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment according to Law, and haſt no certain known Laws ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of God or the Land, as thy rule of direction to guide and lead thee in the ways of right juſtice, to give judgement upon them, nor can manifeſt no true commiſſion to put any known Law in execution.</p>
            <p>It remains certainly true, That thou art no competent Judg to paſs the ſentence of death upon men and women; thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Authority is but an uſurped thing, whereby thou wouldſt deſtroy and oppreſſe them; and it's ſaid; That every oppreſſion againſt Law by colour of any uſurped Authority, is a kind of deſtruction; and it is the worſt oppreſſion that is done by colour of office, <hi>Cook</hi> 2. par. <hi>Inſt. fol.</hi> 48. And thy proceed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings are no better then oppreſſion againſt Law both of God and the Land, and is done by colour of Office under pretence of chief Judge, and in obedience to thy pretended Commiſſion: Therefore the acts of injuſtice done by thee in condemning the ſouls and bodies of men as aforeſaid, is oppreſſion againſt Law, and the worſt kind of deſtruction.</p>
            <p>And if injuſtice be ſo hateful a thing in the eye of the Law, that it deſerves to have judgement (in a high meaſure) turned backward upon it, eſpecially when it is done by colour of office, to make the parties offending, examples to others, that Juſtice may alſo turn back into its courſe; how much more hateful a thing is iujuſtice then in the eye of the Lord, eſpecially when it is done by colour of Office? Doth it not deſerve to have his juſt and righteous judgement (in a high meaſure) turned backward upon it, to make the parties offending, examples to others, that they may fear to do the like, and that his Juſtice may ſtand and remain in its courſe; but we are ſure that the judgement of God is according to truth againſt them which commit ſuch things, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.1, 2. And by the Law of God it is
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:105803:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>declared, <hi>That if a falſe witneſs do but riſe up againſt a man to teſtifie againſt him that which is wrong, then both the men between whom the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troverſie is, ſhall ſtand before the Lord and before the Judge that ſhall be in thoſe dayes, and the Judge (as his duty is ſhall make diligent inquiſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (to find out the truth or falſhood of the evidence) and behold, if the Witneſs be (found out to be) a falſe Witneſs, and hath teſtified falſly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt his brother, then ſhall ye do unto him as he had thought to have done unto his brother, ſo ſhalt thou put away the evil from among you; and thoſe which remain, ſhall hear, and fear, and ſhall henceforth commit no more any ſuch evil among you; thine eye ſhall not pity, but life ſhall go for life, eye for eye, tooth for tooth, hand for hand, Deut.</hi> 19.15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21. or the like judgment was to be executed on a falſe Witneſs, that had been due to the nature of the offence of him that he was an evidence againſt, if his Teſtimony given in evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence againſt him had been true; whereby God hath ſignified his high diſpleaſure againſt injuſtice done by colour of office; for if a falſe evidence had been taken for truth, and the judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment grounded upon the evidence, it had been falſe judgment, as thine is; and falſe judgement is not owned by the Law of God, who commands <hi>to execute true judgement, and to ſhew mercy and compaſſion every man to his brother, Zech.</hi> 7.9. <hi>Mic.</hi> 6.8. <hi>and forbids to wreſt judgement, Exod.</hi> 23.6. ſaying alſo by way of command, <hi>Thou ſhalt not raiſe a falſe report, put not thine hand with the wicked to be an unrighteous Witneſſe,</hi> Exo. 23.1. <hi>Thou ſhalt not follow a multitude to do evil, neither ſhalt thou ſpeak in a cauſe to decline after many, to wreſt judgement,</hi> Exo. 23.2. <hi>Keep thee far from a falſe matter, the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent and righteous ſlay thou not, for I will not juſtifie the wicked,</hi> Exo. 23.7. Likewiſe ſee <hi>Moſes</hi> charge to the Judges, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.16, 17. <hi>they were commanded to judge the people with juſt judgement,</hi> Deut. 16.18. <hi>they were forbidden to wreſt judgement, and were not to pervert the words of the righteous,</hi> Deut. 16.19. <hi>And that which is altogether juſt, they were commanded to follow,</hi> Deut. 16.20. But thou doſt not ſo.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Conſider then, that thou haſt not only done injuſtice both in the eye of the Law, and of the Lord, but alſo thou haſt done the ſame by colour of office: Firſt, in the eye of the Law thou haſt done it, becauſe thou preſumes to paſs the ſentence of Death upon the bodies of men and women, as a pretend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:105803:8" rendition="simple:additions"/>Judge, and haſt no certain outward known Laws as a rule of Direction to guide thee in the ways of right Juſtice to give judgement upon them, nor can produce no commiſſion to put any known Law in execution, or impower thee ſo to do; and are therefore no competent Judge in that matter. And ſecond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, injuſtice in the eye of the Lord thou haſt done, and alſo by colour of office under pretence of chief Judge in the world, and by a pretended commiſſion of the Spirit, pretended to be received from a God <hi>without thee, that ſpake</hi> (thou ſaiſt) <hi>by voice of words to the hearing of the ear.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Conſider the nature of thy offence, how far it extends it ſelf, and that is, <hi>to paſs the ſentence of eternal death and damnation both upon the bodyes and ſouls of men and women, and that to Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Conſider, that thy injuſtice done by colour of office, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves to have a puniſhment proportionable to the offence; and can the offence in the eye of the Lord be any leſs then ſin againſt the Holy Ghoſt, becauſe thou haſt pretended to do it in the Name of the Holy Ghoſt, and ſo wouldſt make the holy Ghoſt the Author of thy offence, which it is not?</p>
            <p>And ſeeing thou art guilty of ſin againſt the <hi>holy Ghoſt,</hi> there is a puniſhment already proportioned for ſuch an offence; and alſo thou art puniſhable by the Law of the Land for preſuming under pretence of a commiſſion, and as a Judge, to paſs the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of death upon the bodies of men and women, and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tends <hi>to go by as certain a rule in ſo doing, as the Judges of the Land do when they give Judgement according to Law;</hi> which thou haſt no cognizance or right unto, neither haſt thou done ſo, as before I have proved; and I had not medled with the outward Laws of the Land, but that I have ſuch a pretended chief Judge to deal with, to ſhew him his folly and injuſtice done by colour of of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, as <hi>I</hi> have done thee, which thou <hi>Lodowick</hi> maiſt for ever be aſhamed of for preſumptuouſly doing as thou haſt done, who haſt alſo erred in thy judgement, and haſt given it contrary to truth, and againſt the Law of the Land: And it's ſaid, <hi>That if any Judgement be given contrary to the points of the great Charter, it ſhall be undone, and holden for nought,</hi> 25 Ed. 1, 2. and by a Statute made <hi>Anno</hi> 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. it is declared, <hi>That if any thing be done againſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:105803:9" rendition="simple:additions"/>the Law, it ſhall be redreſſed and holden for none,</hi> as thine is, and is therefore reverſed, undone, and holden for nought, Take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice of that.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſaiſt, <hi>That in obedience to thy Commiſſion thou haſt already curſed and damned many hundreds of people both ſoul and body to eternity:</hi> I ſay, the greater is thy preſumption and ſin, who haſt no Right nor Authority to do the ſame; thy judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is contrary to truth, and is againſt the Law of God, and the Law of the Land, and is therefore reverſed and holden for none, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>Whereas thou ſaiſt, <hi>That no infinite ſpirit of Chriſt, nor any God can, or ſhall be able to deliver from thy ſentence and curſe:</hi> I ſay, That is falſe, or no leſs then blaſphemy, and there is a puniſhment due to the nature of the offence: Thou haſt hereby denied Chriſt as he is the Advocate with the Father, and the propitia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion for the ſins of the whole World, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2.1, 2. What a mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable condition art thou in! And how great is thy ſin of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption and folly!</p>
            <p>Wouldſt thou have the great King of Heaven, the Lord who is a great God, and a King above all Gods, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 95.3. and Chriſt Jeſus, who is the Prince of the Kings of the Earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.5. to commit their whole power ſolely to thee, who may abuſe it, as thou haſt done, under pretence of a Commiſſion, and reſerve no power in the Eternal God-head to pardon offences com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted againſt them, and preſerve and ſave poor penitent of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fendors by ſhewing mercy unto them, and forgiving of them? And wouldſt thou have no power reſerved in the Eternal God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head to correct and puniſh thee, and ſuch as thou art, for abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Power and People of God, as thou haſt done? Wouldſt thou make the Eternal Power and Godhead inferior to the Kings of the Earth? Do not they reſerve a pardoning and pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhing power in themſelves, beſides what they give to their Judges by their commiſſion?</p>
            <p>But notwithſtanding thy pretended Commiſſion, falſe Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Doctrine, This I affirm on the behalf of the Lord, and the Eternal God-head, That there is a pardoning and a puniſhing power in them reſerved, beyond thy pretended Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:105803:9"/>
            <p>Firſt, as to the pardoning power, it is declared by them that were ſent of the Lord God and his Spirit, ſaying, <hi>Let the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed forſake his ways, and the unrighteous his thoughts, and let him return to the Lord, and he will have mercy upon him; and to our God, and he will abundantly pardon.</hi> Seeing it is ſo, it remains certainly true, that there is a pardoning power reſerved, and remains in the Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal God-head; and it alſo remains true, That the unrighteous and wicked upon the forſaking of their evil thoughts and wicked ways, and returning to the Lord according to his requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rings, are objects of mercy, and pardonable as aforeſaid, which is contrary to thy falſe doctrine and judgement.</p>
            <p>Secondly, As to the pardoning power, that remains in the God-head, is manifeſted in Chriſt, whom God the Father hath exalted with his right hand to be a Prince and a Saviour, for to give repentance unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and forgiveneſs of ſins; and we are his Witneſſes of theſe things, and ſo is the Holy Ghoſt whom God hath given to them that obey him, <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31, 32.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Chriſt Jeſus who is the chief Judge ordained of God to judge the quick and the dead, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.40, 41, 42. he hath manifeſted the pardoning power that remains with the God-head, by ſhewing of mercy, and forgiving offences. The Scribes and the Phariſees ſought an occaſion againſt him (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was merciful and forgave ſins) <hi>and they took a woman-ſinner, and brought her to Chriſt, and ſet her in the midſt;</hi> Firſt, They brought her before Chriſt, and ſet her as an offender before the Judge. Secondly, They accuſed her unto him of the act of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dultery, <hi>John</hi> 8.1, 2, 3, 4. Thirdly, They pleaded both Law and Fact to make their caſe good, and to have ſhut up Chriſt's mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy and compaſſion againſt her, to have moved him to give judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon her, who it's like thought he could not otherwiſe have done, if he owned <hi>Moſes</hi> Law; and if he had denyed it, then they would had an occaſion againſt him, which they ſought for: They pleaded Fact, ſaying, <hi>Maſter, This woman was taken in Adultery, in the very act,</hi> Joh. 8.4. Then they pleaded Law, ſaying, <hi>Now Moſes in the Law commanded that ſuch ſhould be ſtoned,</hi> Joh. 8.5. <hi>But what ſaiſt thou? This they ſaid, tempting of him, that they might have to accuſe him,</hi> John 8.6. <hi>And they continued asking of him,</hi> John 8.7. <hi>ſhewing how earneſt they were to have had
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:105803:10" rendition="simple:additions"/>an accuſation againſt him;</hi> they tempted him for that very end, and to ſee if he would deny putting <hi>Moſes</hi> Law in execution upon that woman which they had taken in Adultery, and brought before him to accuſe unto him.</p>
            <p>But Jeſus himſelf, who was chief Judge ordained of God, and had power or authority given him to execute judgement, <hi>John</hi> 5.22, 27. he did neither accuſe the offender, nor counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance thoſe bloody accuſers that brought her before him, though they pleaded both Law and Fact unto him, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, who teacheth by his example in that caſe, That it is not the duty of a Court to accuſe any, though a known offender, nor to countenance bloody accuſers, but rather to mollifie their rigour, as Chriſt did in the ſame caſe, who in great wiſdom an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered their queſtion, and ſaid unto them, <hi>He that is without ſin among you, let him firſt caſt a ſtone at her,</hi> Joh. 8.7. (or put <hi>Moſes</hi> Law in execution upon her) but thoſe accuſers were none of them without ſin, becauſe they ſinned in tempting of Chriſt, and the Witneſs of God in their own conſcience teſtified the ſame unto them, whereby they were convicted, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>went out one by one, beginning at the eldeſt, even unto the laſt; and Jeſus was left alone, and the woman ſtanding in the midſt, John</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>Firſt, By which wiſe anſwer of his, he put a ſtop to their cruelty againſt the offender, and thereby he delivered her from their cruelty, and took her into his mercy, who knew better how to deal with her, then they would have had him.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He by that gracious wiſe anſwer unto them, put a ſtop to their ſubtilty, and croſt their intent which they had in their minds in their temptation againſt him.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, He hath ſhewed by that wiſe anſwer unto them, That criminal perſons are no competent Judges to condemn others for that which themſelves are guilty of.</p>
            <p n="4">4. He alſo by that wiſe anſwer unto them, preſerved himſelf out of their ſnare, for he thereby owned <hi>Moſes</hi> Law in its time and place, which if he had then denyed, they thought to have had an occaſion againſt him, or whereof to have accuſed him, and having preſerved himſelf out of their ſnare, and taken the woman ſinner out of their cruelty, into his mercy, as aforeſaid;
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:105803:10"/>He then as a gracious and merciful Judge looked upon her with an eye of compaſſion, ſaying, <hi>Woman, where are all thoſe thine accuſers? Hath no man condemned thee,</hi> Joh. 8.10. <hi>She anſwer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and ſaid, No man, Lord.</hi> And Jeſus to manifeſt his mercy, and the pardoning power which remained with the God-head, he ſaid, <hi>Neither do I condemn thee; go, and ſin no more,</hi> Joh. 8.10, 11.</p>
            <p>And as a merciful Judge he forgave her that offence, and ſet her free, and gave her commend to abſtain from ſin for the time to come, ſaying, <hi>Go, and ſin no more;</hi> as much as to ſay, let mercy held forth in forgiving thy offence that is paſt, engage thy heart againſt ſin, and unto God for the time to come.</p>
            <p>But though thou <hi>Lodowick</hi> pretend to be the chief Judge in the World, thy example, doctrine and practice teacheth quite contrary to the doctrine and example of Chriſt, whereby it appears, and is plainly made manifeſt, That thou art not ordained chief Judge in his ſtead.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Thy Example, Doctrine and Practice teacheth to be both Judge, Accuſer and Witneſs, contrary to the <hi>Law</hi> of God, and the Law of the Land.</p>
            <p>Secondly, To condemn at a diſtance without any due courſe of Law, or orderly proceedings, before thou have the parties and their Accuſers face to face before thee, to hear what they can ſay.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, To condemn at will and pleaſure, contrary to any known Law either of God or the Land.</p>
            <p n="4">4. It teacheth not the preſervation of any known Law, but rather the deſtruction of all known Laws both of God and the land.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Thy example, doctrine and practice teacheth to condemn the bodies of men and women without any known law either of God or the land, as a rule of direction to guide and lead in the ways of right Juſtice, to give judgement upon them ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cordingly.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Thou teacheſt thereby, That if judgement or ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence be given, pronounced, or paſt, though never ſo contrary to truth, it ought not to be redreſſed or reverſed, undone and holden for nothing; which is quite contrary to the law of the
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:105803:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>land: And we are ſure that the judgement of God is according to truth, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2.2. but thine is not ſo; whereby it is evident, that it is not the judgement of God.</p>
            <p>It appears and is evident, firſt, That thou art an unlawful Judge, becauſe thou preſumes to paſs the ſentence of death up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the bodies of men and women without cognizance or law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Authority ſo to do.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That thou art a fooliſh unwiſe Judge, becauſe thou paſſeſt the ſentence of death upon the bodies of men and woman at a diſtance from thee, without having them and their anſwers face to face before thee.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, That thou art an unjuſt Judge, becauſe thou paſſeſt the ſentence of death upon the bodies of men and women con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to truth, without any known laws either of God or the Land, as a Rule of direction to guide and lead thee in the ways of right juſtice, to give judgement upon them accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That thou art a cruel unmerciful Judge, becauſe if thy ſentence be once pronounced and paſt (though it be never ſo erroneous and falſe) thou wouldſt have it impoſſible for any God to reverſe and undo the ſame, or to deliver there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>from.</p>
            <p>Seeing that it is ſo, it remains certainly true, That thou art no true and competent Judge, neither ordained of God nor man to paſs the ſentence of death upon the bodies of men and women; and it remains as true, That the ſouls in the Father's hand thou haſt nothing to do withal.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe Chriſt giveth to them eternal life, and they ſhall never periſh, <hi>John</hi> 10.28.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe no man is able to pluck them out of the Father's hand, as it is written <hi>John</hi> 10.29.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, Becauſe the Gates of Hell ſhall not prevail againſt them.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe it remains true, That thou art not the choſen Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of the Spirit of Truth, and that thou haſt not received thy pretended Commiſſion from the God of Truth, to do as thou haſt done, and pretendeſt to do by colour thereof.</p>
            <pb n="19" facs="tcp:105803:11" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe thou denies Almighty God himſelf.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe thou denies Chriſt Jeſus of his Offices.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Becauſe thou denies him of his Officers, as Meſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, Miniſters or Ambaſſadors.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Becauſe thou denies the holy Scriptures.</p>
            <p>Fifthly, Becauſe thou haſt lyed againſt God and Chriſt, and haſt born a falſe Teſtimony of them, and of the true Prophets of God, and Apoſtles of Chriſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. As to the firſt, That thou denies Almighty God himſelf, is evident by thy own Doctrine, becauſe thou ſaiſt, <hi>That the dead after death ſhall never ſee any other God or Judge but the remembrance of that Sentence which you the pretended Witneſſes of the Spirit did paſs upon them in this life;</hi> which is quite contrary to the doctrine of Chriſt, and the Scriptures of truth, <hi>John</hi> 5.26, 27, 28, 29. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25.31, 32, 33, 34; 41. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.9.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And as to the ſecond, that thou denieſt Chriſt of his offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, is evident againſt thee by thy own doctrine in three parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars. Firſt, Thou denieſt Chriſt as chief Judge ordained of God, to ſet up thy ſelf in his ſtead; becauſe thou ſaiſt, <hi>Thou art ordained chief Judge in the world to give ſentence upon men and women ſpiritual and eternal, and what ſhall become of them after dea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>h,</hi> contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to the Doctrine of Chriſt, and the Scriptures of truth, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25 31, 32. &amp;c. <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.26, 27, 28, 29, 30. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.42 &amp; 17.31. 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4 1 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4.5. and as before is proved. Secondly, Thou denieſt Chriſt as he is the Saviour of men, and the Author of eternal ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to all that obey him; in whom eternal life is to be had, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou accounts that there is no eternal life to be had but in the faith of thy doctrine, ſaying, <hi>There is no eternal life to be had but in the faith of the doctrine or declaration of a Prophet who hath a Commiſſion from God;</hi> &amp; ſaith, <hi>There neither is, nor ever ſhall be any ſuch Prophet but thy ſelf whilſt the world endureth.</hi> In anſwer to the which I ſay, That the holy Scriptures which were ſpoken and declared from the movings of the Holy Ghoſt in the holy men of God, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20, 21. were better doctrine &amp; declaration of Prophets of God then thine, who had a better commiſſion or authority from God then ever thou hadſt. And concerning their declaration, Chriſt ſaid to the Jews, <hi>Search the Scriptures, for in them ye think ye have eternal life, &amp; they are they which teſtifie of me, and ye will not come
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:105803:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>to me that ye might have life, Iohn</hi> 5.39, 40. And Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, <hi>I am the way, and the truth, and the life; no man cometh un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Father but by me, Ioh.</hi> 14.6. And the Ambaſſador of Chriſt hath declared and ſaid, <hi>That the wages of ſin is death, but the gift of God is eternal life through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord,</hi> as it is written <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.22 23. (then not in the faith of thy doctrine.) And Chriſt doth give unto his ſheep eternal life, and they ſhall never periſh, neither ſhall any man pluck them out of his hand, <hi>Ioh</hi> 10.27, 28. And the Meſſengers of Chriſt have declared and ſaid, <hi>This is the record that God hath given to us eternal life, and this life is in his Son,</hi> 1 <hi>Ioh.</hi> 5.11. (then not in the faith of thy doctrine.) <hi>He that hath the Son, hath life eternal,</hi> though he deny thy doctrine; <hi>and he that hath not the Son, hath not life eternal,</hi> though he may have faith in thy doctrine.</p>
            <p>By what hath been ſaid, it is evident, and remains certainly true:</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Chriſt Jeſus is the Saviour of men, and the Author of eternal ſalvation to all that obey him. <hi>Acts</hi> 5.31, 32. <hi>Heb.</hi> 7 25 <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.9. <hi>and is able to ſave to the uttermoſt all that come unto God by him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That <hi>he is the way to the Father, without which no man can come unto him, Iohn</hi> 146</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>That the gift of God is eternal life, which Chriſt doth give unto his ſheep that they may never periſh, Rom.</hi> 6.23. <hi>Iohn</hi> 10.27, 28.</p>
            <p n="4">4. That eternal life is not in the faith of thy doctrine or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration, but in Chriſt the Son, according to the Record that God hath given, <hi>For he that hath the Son, hath life, and he that hath not the Son, hath not life,</hi> as it is written 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.11, 12.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Thou denieſt Chriſt as he is the Advocate with the Father, and the propitiation for the ſins of the whole World, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou ſaiſt, <hi>That no infinite Spirit of Chriſt, nor any God can, or ſhall be able to deliver from thy ſentence and curſe;</hi> which is contrary to truth, and the holy Scripture, where it is ſaid, <hi>My little children, theſe things write I unto you, that ye ſin not; and if any man ſin, we have an Advocate with the Father, Ieſus Chriſt the righteous, and he is the propitiation for our ſins, and not for ours only, but alſo for the ſins of the whole world,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.1, 2. <hi>Wherefore he is able alſo to ſave them to the uttermoſt that come unto God by him, ſeeing he ever liveth to make interceſſion for them;</hi> as it is written, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.25.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:105803:12"/>
            <p n="3">3. And as to the third, That thou denieſt Chriſt of his officers, is evident by thy own doctrine, becauſe thou falſly ſaiſt, <hi>That no man ought to officiate the Office of a Miniſter, Meſſenger of Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of Chriſt, but ſuch as are appointed by</hi> John Reeves <hi>and thy ſelf;</hi> contrary to the Scriptures, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 4 10, 11 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10, 11 12. <hi>Acts</hi> 13.2.4. <hi>Acts</hi> 20 28. <hi>Acts</hi> 10, 19, 20, 21. <hi>Acts</hi> 11.12, 21. <hi>Acts</hi> 10.42, 43 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1, 2, 3 4, 5, 6, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7. and as before I have proved.</p>
            <p n="4">4. And as to the fourth, That thou denieſt the holy Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, I prove againſt thee by thy own doctrine; firſt, becauſe thou ſaiſt, <hi>That the words which Chriſt ſaid to his Diſciples, Bleſs, and curſe not, concerns not thee nor any man upon earth at this day;</hi> contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt, where it is ſaid, <hi>Whoſoever therefore ſhall break one of theſe leaſt commandments, and teach men ſo, he ſhall be called the leaſt in the Kingdom of Heaven; but whoſoever ſhall do and teach them, he ſhall be called great in the Kingdom of Heaven,</hi> Matt. 5.17, 18, 19. <hi>and one jot or tittle ſhall in no wiſe paſs till all be fulfilled.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, Thou denieſt the holy Scriptures, becauſe thou ſaiſt, <hi>The dead after death ſhall never ſee any other God or Iudge but the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance of that ſentence which you the pretended Witneſſes of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit did paſſe upon them in this life;</hi> contrary to the Scriptures, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I have proved.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, Thou denieſt the holy Scriptures, becauſe thou ſaiſt, <hi>Thou art chief Iudge ordained of God to give ſentence upon men and wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men ſpiritual and eternal, and what ſhall become of them after death;</hi> contrary to the Scriptures, and as before I have proved.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Thou denieſt the Scriptures, becauſe thou ſaiſt, <hi>That no man ought to officiate the Office of a Miniſter, Meſſenger or Ambaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſador of Chriſt, but ſuch as are appointed by</hi> John Reeves <hi>&amp; thy ſelf;</hi> contrary to the Scriptures, and as before I have proved.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, Thou denieſt the Scriptures, becauſe thou accounts them, but <hi>the dead Letter of other mens words, whoſe Light thou judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt to be but dark in compariſon of that Light which comes by thy preten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded Commiſſion;</hi> contrary to the Scriptures, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.20, 21, 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.5.7 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4 6, 7. 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p n="5">5. And as to the fifth, That thou haſt lyed againſt God, and againſt Chriſt, and born a falſe Teſtimony of them, and of the holy Prophets of God, and Apoſtles of Chriſt, is evident
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:105803:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>by what hath already been ſaid, and alſo further appears that it is ſo; becauſe it is certainly true, That the holy Scriptures were ſpoken forth from God himſelf, and alſo from Chriſt Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus our Lord; and likewiſe according to the movings of the ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Ghoſt in the holy men of God, both Prophets and Apoſtles: And it is as true, that their Light who ſpoke forth the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, were not dark in compariſon of that Light which comes by thy pretended Commiſſion: Therefore it is evident and certainly true, That thou haſt lyed againſt them, and born a falſe Teſtimony of them, as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For God is Light, and in him is no darkneſs at all,</hi> 1 Joh. 1.5. How then can thy pretended Light of thy pretended Commiſſion, be greater then God the Fountain of Light? I ſay, it is not. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it is evident, That thou haſt lyed againſt God, account<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that he who is the Fountain of Light, is but dark in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of that Light which comes by thy pretended Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion.</p>
            <p>Chriſt hath declared himſelf to be the Light of the World, <hi>John</hi> 8.12. and <hi>he is the true Light which lighteth every man that com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth into the world, Ioh.</hi> 1.9. but thou art not that Light, neither art thou like unto it: And in accounting Chriſt who is the true Light, as aforeſaid, to be but dark in compariſon of thine, thou haſt lyed againſt him.</p>
            <p>And <hi>David</hi> declared and ſaid, the Lord was his Light; <hi>Pſ.</hi> 27.1. &amp; he ſpoke forth Scriptures: And to them that ſpoke forth Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures as the words &amp; true ſayings of God from the mouth of the Lord, he was, and is an everlaſting Light and glory, according to his promiſe, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 60.19, 20. but ſo art not thou; therefore thou haſt lyed and born a falſe Teſtimony, ſaying, <hi>That their Light who ſpoke forth the Scriptures, was but dark in compariſon of thine;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold what a falſe Witneſſe thou art; take notice how thou art confuted.</p>
            <p>And whereas thou ſaiſt, <hi>That after thy ſentence is paſt upon the Spea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers, they ſhall never grow more to any great experience, neither ſhall they have thoſe Viſions &amp; Revelations and Revelations from that Light within them, as they had before; but ſhall rather wither and decline.</hi> It ſeems thou accounts that they have great experience, and both Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Revelations from the Light within, until thy (falſe) ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:105803:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>be paſt upon them; and ſeeing it is ſo, I ſay, thy ſentence can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not hinder the ſame, nor their growth into great experience of truth, neither at all cauſe them to wither or decline therefrom; thy teſtimony is falſe in that reſpect, as well as it is againſt God and Chriſt, and as aforeſaid.</p>
            <p>And whereas in thy imagination thou haſt accuſed the <hi>Quakers</hi> to be of the nature and ſeed of the Serpent, and by thy preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion haſt given judgement accordingly; yet notwithſtanding to ſignifie that lyars and falſe Witneſſes ſtand in need of a good me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory leſt they contradict themſelves, and confute their evidence; for want of which thou haſt contradicted thy ſelf, and by thy ſelf-confutation haſt cleared the <hi>Quakers</hi> from thy falſe accuſation and judgement grounded thereupon, by ſaying the <hi>Quakers</hi> do preach from the Scriptures and Light within, and that Devils are caſt out, and much good is done by them; and I ſay, ſuch are not of the nature and ſeed of the Serpent; thou haſt by thy own con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>futation cleared them therefrom, as before in a former Writing I have proved.</p>
            <p>And to conclude, I do affirm, That there is a puniſhing power reſerved in the Eternal Godhead, and doth therewith remain to puniſh the rebellious, obſtinate and preſumptuous, ſuch as thou art, or as may be read <hi>Heb.</hi> 10.26, 27, 28, 29, 30, 31. 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. <hi>Iude</hi> 5.6. For we know him that hath ſaid, <hi>Vengeance belongeth unto me, I will recompence, ſaith the Lord,</hi> Heb. 10.30. <hi>For God will eaſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of his Enemies</hi> (ſuch as thou art) <hi>and he will be avenged of his Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries,</hi> as it is written. And ſeeing vengeance is the Lords, I leave it to him to repay thee according to the nature of thy offences, or as his in juſtice he is pleaſed to do.</p>
            <div type="letter">
               <head>Concerning the two Witneſſes, &amp;c.</head>
               <opener>
                  <salute>Lodowick,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IF <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf were joint Commiſſioners, and had your pretended Commiſſion (not ſeverally aſunder, but) joint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly together, hath not the death of <hi>John Reeves</hi> made void thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Commiſſion to all intents, conſtructions &amp; purpoſes what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever? Or, if <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf did pretend to be the two Witneſſes ſpoken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 113. and to have the power given to them; hath not the death of <hi>John Reeves</hi> made it evident againſt you, to be none of them, becauſe it is ſaid concerning thoſe two Witneſſes <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. That <hi>until they had finiſhed their teſtimony, if any man
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:105803:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>would hurt them, fire ſhould proceed out of their mouth, and devour their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies: And when they ſhould have finiſhed their teſtimony, the Beaſt that aſcendeth out of the bottomleſs pit ſhould make war againſt them, and ſhould overcome them, and kill them,</hi> Rev. 11.7. And it is ſaid concerning them, that <hi>their dead bodies ſhould lye in the ſtreet of the great City, and they of the people, and kindreds, and nations ſhould ſee their dead bodies three dayes and a half, and ſhould not ſuffer their dead bodies to be put in graves, Rev.</hi> 11.8, 9. but it was not ſo with <hi>John Reeves;</hi> whereby it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, That he was not one of them Witneſſes.</p>
               <p>Likewiſe it is ſaid concerning thoſe two Witneſſes, That <hi>after three dayes and a half the Spirit of Life from God entered into them, and they ſtood upon their feet, and great fear fell upon them which ſaw them,</hi> Rev. 11.11. But it was not ſo with <hi>John Reeves,</hi> that the Spirit of Life en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered into him, to cauſe him to ſtand upon his feet after he had been dead three days and a half, neither did any ſee him ſo, after he was dead, to cauſe great fear to fall upon them; whereby it is manifeſt, That <hi>John Reeves</hi> was not one of thoſe Witneſſes.</p>
               <p>Moreover it is ſaid of thoſe two Witneſſes, That they aſcended up to Heaven in a Cloud (but ſo did not <hi>John Reeves</hi>) and their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies beheld them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.12. and <hi>the ſame hour there was a great Earth-quake, and the tenth part of the City fell; and in the Earthquake were ſlain of men ſeven thouſand, and the reninant were affrighted, and gave glory to the God of Heaven.</hi> Rev. 11.13.</p>
               <p>And as it is evident, That <hi>John Reeves</hi> was not one of thoſe Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes ſpoken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3. by what hath been ſaid, &amp; as aforemen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, meant and intended; ſo likewiſe it is evident, That thou <hi>Lodowick</hi> art not the other of them two Witneſſes, becauſe it is ſaid of them, (that in order to the finiſhing of their Teſtimony) <hi>They ſhould propheſie a thouſand two hundred and threeſcore dayes clothed in ſack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cloth, Rev.</hi> 11.3. But when didſt thou ſo? And it is ſaid concerning them, <hi>That if any man will hurt them, fire proceedeth out of their mouth, and devoureth their enemies; and if any man will hurt them, he muſt in that manner be killed,</hi> Rev. 11.5. <hi>Theſe have power to ſhut heaven, that it rain not in the days of their Propheſie; and have power over waters, to turn them into blood, Rev.</hi> 11.6. But when didſt thou propheſie a thouſand two hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and threeſcore days in ſack cloth? And when did fire proceed out of thy mouth to kill any? And when didſt thou ſhut up the hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens that it did not rain during the time of thy pretended prophe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie? Or when didſt thou turn the waters into blood, whereby it might have been made manifeſt, that thou hadſt been one of them,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:105803:14" rendition="simple:additions"/>who couldſt manifeſt no ſuch thing by thy pretended Commiſſion, and the greatneſs of thy pretended power? Whereby it is mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt that thou art not one of thoſe Witneſſes.</p>
               <p>And ſeeing thou pretends a new Commiſſion which is not owned by the Scriptures, or by the Doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, &amp; ſaiſt, <hi>Thou haſt received power ſince to the contrary;</hi> (to vindicate thy cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing and damning:) When was the new Covenant and Miniſtry of the Goſpel changed? Or how canſt thou make it appear by the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, that it is not ſo, ſeeing thou pretends a contrary Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to what the Scriptures or the Doctrine of Chriſt &amp; his Apoſtles do own. And it is ſaid concerning Chriſt and the new Covenant, that he hath obtained a more excellent Miniſtry (then that of the old Covenant) by how much alſo he is the Mediator of a better Covenant, which was eſtabliſhed upon better promiſes, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. <hi>And becauſe he continueth for ever, he hath an unchangea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Prieſthood</hi> (or Miniſtry) <hi>wherefore he is able to ſave them to the uttermoſt that come unto God by him, becauſe he ever liveth to make inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion for them,</hi> as it is written <hi>Heb.</hi> 7.24, 25.</p>
               <p>And if none ought to officiate the office of a Miniſter, Meſſenger or Ambaſſador of Chriſt, but ſuch as are appointed by <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf (as thou ſaiſt) wouldſt not thou have the Miniſtry changed now during thy life? and wouldſt not thou have the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtry of the Goſpel to ceaſe and dye at thy death, becauſe thou ſaiſt, <hi>Thou art the laſt that ever ſhall ſpeak by Commiſſion from God;</hi> and <hi>that the Lord will never chuſe any more after thee whilſt the world doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And it is evident, That thou wouldſt have ſuch a Miniſtry as the Scriptures no where own, and quite contrary to the Doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and not at all owned by the New-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant and Miniſtry of the Goſpel.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Becauſe thoſe who are appointed by <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf to officiate the office of a Miniſter, Meſſenger, or Ambaſſador of Chriſt, are ſuch as are not choſen of God to that Work.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe that are appointed by <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf to the Work of the Miniſtry, are ſuch as have no commiſſion from God to impower them to officiate the office of a Miniſter, Meſſenger or Ambaſſador of Chriſt, and are therefore very unfit for ſo great and glorious a Work.</p>
               <p n="3">3. They are ſuch as are never like to have any Commiſſion from God to impower them to the Work of the Miniſtry, whilſt the
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:105803:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>World doth endure, and that according to thy own doctrine.</p>
               <p n="4">4. They are ſuch as know not the Scriptures, neither can they truly interpret the Scriptures, and that according to thy own ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings:</p>
               <p>Becauſe (for proof thereof.) thou ſaiſt, <hi>That thou art the choſen Witneſs of the Spirit, and the laſt that ever ſhall ſpeak by Commiſſion from God:</hi> Then not thoſe that are appointed by <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf, they neither have, nor are not like to have any commiſſion from God to impower them to the work of the Miniſtry; thou haſt excluded them from that by thy pretended commiſſion, and the Doctrine thereof. Take notice of that.</p>
               <p>And thou ſaiſt, <hi>That God will never chuſe any more after thee whilſt the world doth endure:</hi> If ſo, then God will never chuſe thoſe that are appointed by <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf: Therefore they are no fit Miniſters, Meſſengers or Ambaſſadors of Chriſt that are appointed by <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf: Firſt, Becauſe they are not choſen of God to that Work, nor ever like to be whilſt the World doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure Secondly, Becauſe they have no commiſſion from God to im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>power them to ſo great and glorious a Work. And thirdly, Becauſe (according to thy doctrine) they are never like to have any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion from God to impower them (whilſt the World doth en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure) to officiate the office of Miniſters, Meſſengers or Ambaſſadors of Chriſt; and there is no need for them to officiate the office afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, after the end of the world. Mind how thou art confuted.</p>
               <p>And thou ſaiſt, <hi>No man knows the Scriptures but thy ſelf, nor no man can truly interpret the Scriptures but thy ſelf;</hi> if ſo, then not thoſe that are appointed by <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thee to the Work of the Miniſtry, if none ought to officiate the office of a Miniſter, Meſſenger or Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador of Chriſt, but ſuch as are appointed by <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thy ſelf: And ſeeing that thoſe whom you appoint, are not fit for that Work, thou haſt as much as in thee lieth, excluded all the Miniſters, Meſſengers and Ambaſſadors of Chriſt from the work of the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry; take notice of that. And all may behold thy preſumption &amp; folly, and how thou art confuted, enſnared, and taken in thy own craftineſs; at which thou maiſt bluſh, &amp; for evermore be aſhamed of. Silence deceit and Deceiver; let truth ſtop thy mouth, and all ſuch, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.11.</p>
               <p>By what hath been ſaid, it is evident, and remains certainly true; 1. That <hi>John Reeves</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Muggleton</hi> are not the two Witneſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes ſpoken of <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.3. neither are they in any thing like unto them
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:105803:15"/>2. That the New-Covenant which Chriſt Jeſus is the Mediator of is eſtabliſh'd upon better promiſes then the old Covenant was. 3. That That the Miniſtry of the Goſpel is a more excellent Miniſtry. 4. That the Prieſthood of Chriſt, or the Miniſtry of the Goſpel is an unchangeable Prieſthood or Miniſtry. 5 That Chriſt the Saints High Prieſt, &amp; Mediator of the New-covenant, is able to ſave them to the uttermoſt that come unto God by him, becauſe he ever li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth to make interceſſion for them. 6. That none who are appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by <hi>John Reeves</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Muggleton,</hi> ought to officiate the of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of a Miniſter, Meſſenger or Ambaſſador of Chriſt, becauſe all who are appointed by <hi>John Reeves</hi> and <hi>Lodowick Muggleton,</hi> to the Work of the Miniſtry, are very unfit for ſo great &amp; glorious a work. 7. That the deceit ought to be ſilent; or, that the Deceiver &amp; thou <hi>Lodowick</hi> ought to let Truth ſtop thy mouth, like a falſe Prophet as thou art, whoſe mouths muſt be ſtopped, according to <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.11.</p>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <head>Poſtſcript: Or, Concerning Error, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IF none know the Scriptures but thy ſelf; then not thoſe that are appointed by <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thee to the work of the Miniſtry. And as Chriſt ſaid to the <hi>Sadduces</hi> when they came to ask him whoſe Wife ſhe might be in the reſurrection which ſeven brethren had had to wife, becauſe they all had her; in anſwer thereunto he ſaid, <hi>Ye err, not knowing the Scriptures nor the power of God,</hi> Matth. <hi>22.23, 24, 25, 26, 27, 28, 29.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>So ſay I to thee, That thoſe who are appointed by <hi>John Reeves</hi> and thee to the work of the Miniſtry, they err not knowing the Scriptures nor the pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of God, becauſe thou ſaiſt, No man knows the Scriptures but thy ſelf: Therefore inaſmuch as they err not knowing the Scriptures, they muſt needs err in their expoſitions, meanings, pretended preachings and interpretation of Scriptures; ſo that their pretended preaching of Scriptures is error. <hi>2.</hi> Their meanings and conceivings of the Scriptures is error. <hi>3.</hi> Their expoſitions and pretended interpretations of Scriptures is error. And inaſmuch as they err, not knowing the Scriptures, they alſo err not knowing the power of God from whence the holy Scripture is given by inſpiration of God, <hi>2 Tim. 3.16.</hi> And ſo their whole work about your pretended Miniſtry, is no better then error, and muſt needs therefore be very unprofitable, and not fit to be owned.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="letter">
               <opener>
                  <salute>Lodowick,</salute>
               </opener>
               <p>IN thy pretended Anſwer (bearing date <hi>May</hi> 8.1663.) to a Letter of mine to thee, entitled, <hi>Falſe judgement reverſed, and againſt te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified;</hi>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:105803:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>thou ſaiſt, <hi>Thou ſhalt firſt commend me for ſetting my name to it. And ſecondly, For ſetting down thy words ſo truly and punctually, that it makes thy Commiſſion and Authority to ſhine the more bright and clear.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>In anſwer thereunto I ſay, It may appear unto all that hears of the ſame, That I have not perverted or wronged thy words or wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings; and alſo, That thou owns thy ſayings, and haſt not repent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of thy errors and blaſphemies, but ſtill perſiſts therein, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joiceth in the ſame; and therefore all to whom this may come to be heard, ſeen and read, may take notice what thou art, and be aware of thee and thy deceit.</p>
               <p>Thou ſaiſt, <hi>That thou art as true an Ambaſſador of God, and Judge of mens ſpiritual eſtate, as any ever was ſince the Creation of the world,</hi> &amp; thou only ſaiſt it, but leaves it as proofleſs as the reſt; but I do deny it, therefore prove it if thou canſt. And whereas thou ſaiſt, <hi>If you Qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers and others can ſatisfie your ſelves. that there never was any man com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſionated of God to bleſs and curſe, then you ſhall all eſcape that curſe that I have pronounced apon ſo many hundreds, and I only ſhall ſuffer for curſing others without a Commiſſion from God.</hi> I ſay in anſwer unto thee, What is all this to the purpoſe? Admit that we grant that God did commiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionate under the Law to bleſs &amp; to curſe, what is that to thee? muſt it neceſſarily follow, that thou art ſo commiſſionated? We are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied by the Lord, and aſſured to the contrary; and we know that we ſhall eſcape that curſe which thou haſt pronounced, and are ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied, That thou ſhalt ſuffer for curſing ſo many hundreds with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out a Commiſſion from God, as thou haſt done.</p>
               <p>And whereas thou ſaiſt, That <hi>thy Commiſſion is no pretended thing, but as true as</hi> Moſes, <hi>the Prophets and Apoſtles Commiſſion was:</hi> I do de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny it, prove that if thou canſt; or elſe let it be granted for true, That thou haſt taken upon thee to lye in the Name of the Lord, &amp; that thy pretended Commiſſion is but a counterfeit thing, as doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs it is; and therefore thou maiſt expect a puniſhment propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionable to thy offence.</p>
               <p>And whereas thou ſaiſt, <hi>That no man can come to the aſſurance of the favour of God now in theſe dayes, but in believing that God gave this power unto</hi> John Reeves <hi>and thy ſelf:</hi> As firſt, That <hi>thou haſt power given over all other Gods and infinite Spirits what ſoever.</hi> 2. <hi>That thou haſt the pardon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing power and the damning power.</hi> 3. <hi>That thou haſt the keys of Heaven and of Hell; and that none can get into Heaven except thou open the gates.</hi> 4. <hi>That thou haſt power to remit their ſins who receive thy doctrine, and to retain and bind their ſins more cloſe upon their conſciences for their deſpiſing or not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiving
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:105803:16"/>of thy doctrine.</hi> 5. <hi>That thou haſt power to bleſs and curſe men and women to eternity.</hi> 6. <hi>That it is not the Light of Chriſt within, nor the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, no nor God without, that ſhall deliver from under thy ſentence and curſe.</hi> 7. <hi>That thou art ſingle in doctrine, knowledge, judgement and power, above all men either Prophets or Apoſtles ſince the beginning of the world, or that ſhall ever be hereafter whilſt the world doth endure.</hi> 8. <hi>That thou art the only Judge of the two ſeeds now in theſe laſt dayes.</hi> 9. <hi>That there is no true Miniſter, Meſſenger nor Ambaſſador of God in the World at this day but thy ſelf; neither ſhall there be any ſent of God after thee to the worlds end.</hi> 10. <hi>That God will have men and women juſtified and condemned no other way but by man like themſelves.</hi> And 11. <hi>This power</hi> (ſaiſt thou) <hi>hath God given unto me, and in this regard I am the only and alone Judge what ſhall become of men and women after death; neither ſhall thoſe that are damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by me, ſee any other God or judge but me.</hi> I ſay, if theſe be not er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, lyes and blaſphemy; what is? Let God and his people by the Spirit of his Son ſent into their hearts, judge in this caſe, whereby it may appear what ſpirit thou art of, and what thy pretended Commiſſion is made up of, even of pride, preſumption, lyes, er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors, falſe judgement, deluſion and blaſphemy, as is apparent.</p>
               <p>And through the aſſiſtance of God the Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, I hope I ſhall ever be ready to teſtifie for the Lord, &amp; againſt thy deceit whilſt I have breath, as thereunto moved &amp; directed by the Lord. And though thou ſay, <hi>That a God without thee ſpoke to thee by voice of words to the hearing of the ear, when he gave thy pretended Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion unto thee;</hi> yet thou ſaiſt, That <hi>no perſon condemned by thee, can make his appeal unto God neither by himſelf, nor by any other;</hi> and why? thy reaſon is, <hi>Be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>auſe</hi> (ſaiſt thou) <hi>God is not in this world at all.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>I ſay, if it be true, That none can make their appeal to God, nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by themſelves, nor by the Lord Jeſus, that are condemned by thee, becauſe (thou ſaiſt) God is not in this World at all; where was he then when thou received thy pretended Commiſſion, ſeeing thou ſaiſt thou received it from a God without thee, that ſpake by voice of words to the hearing of the ear? Or, is it not a fiction on imagination of thy brain that thou haſt received, and art ſo confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent in? and therefore a ſtrong deluſion. And whereas thou ſaiſt, That <hi>becauſe I am not under the ſentence of thy Commiſſion by verbal words or writing, thou ſhalt give anſwer unto my Letter; for</hi> (ſaiſt thou) <hi>I never give anſwer in writing to any one that is under the ſentence of my Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> I ſay, That's a ready way to ſhuffle off a ſound anſwer, or paſſe by with a lame Reply, or paſſing falſe judgement at a diſtance, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:105803:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>of vindicating &amp; making good what thou art charged with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all; and it ſeems to the end that thou maiſt ſlip off, and leave thy matter as proofleſs as before, thou ſends me a Bill of Excommuni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation or Execration, and paſſeth ſentence to exclude thy ſelf from writing any more in anſwer unto me: A ſhuffling trick of deceit indeed. But this I am bold in the Lord to teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fie unto thee, That thy judgement is falſe and erroneous, both as to matter and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, and is a ſign and token of a falſe Judge that never was ſent of the Lord; <hi>for who ſhall lay any thing to the charge of Gods Elect, ſeeing it is God that juſtifies?</hi> And it is apparent that thou art a falſe Judge, becauſe thou condemns God's Elect under pretence of judging the Serpents Seed. Thou art a Deceiver indeed, and I am bold to tell thee of it, and do teſtifie againſt thee; and thy judgement I value not, it is but like aſhes under the ſoles of my feet, and will never trouble me, becauſe it proceeds from an Antichriſtian ſpirit, and will never be laid to my charge by the Lord. Therefore ſilence Deceiver, and give over thy deceit; for what I have ſaid in vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Truth, and in oppoſition to thy deceit, ſhall ſtand over thee in the ſight of God and his people that are guided by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of his Son ſent into their hearts. And truly I admire that <hi>Doro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy Carter,</hi> or any that are ſober and conſciencious people, ſhould not abhor thy deluſion and wicked abomination; for aſſuredly it is not of God, but of the Devil; and this is my faithful Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony concerning the ſame, and I am not aſhamed to own it under my Name.</p>
               <closer>
                  <signed>R. Farnſworth.</signed>
               </closer>
               <pb facs="tcp:105803:17"/>
            </div>
            <trailer>THE END.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
